Hello friends, thanks for joining us. Uh
Joel, Jenny Lenn and I were part of a
panel uh at General Assembly on behalf
of the Alliance for Mission Renewal. Uh
and now that it's been almost a month
since GA has been over uh and we've been
hither and yan, we thought it might be
great to to get back together again uh
and just to brief a little bit together
uh about how we felt general assembly
went. at least I know for myself is I've
gone around uh my congregation uh
different folks who've been asking me um
so how was GA for you? Uh and we thought
that might be a good prompt question uh
to ask. So Joel Jenny Len, how was GA
for you?
>> Joel, I want to hear your thoughts
before I share mine.
>> Yeah, I think it was um an encouraging
time. Uh, and how you answer that
question always depends on where your
vision is cast in terms of what are we
talking about? Um, are we talking about
the business that was conducted at GA?
Are we talking about the opportunities
to connect with people? Um, are we
talking about some of the vibe uh within
the assembly hall? Because I think my
personal answer is going to vary. Um,
and I think Sean, if I tried to push
that all together in one basket, um, in
in the words of Mr. Darcy from one of
the movie versions of Pride and
Prejudice, I would say GA was perfectly
uh, which it kind of sounds good at
first and then you realize like, wait,
it was fine. It was mid uh, as my kids
would say. That's my take on GA. Glad to
unpack that more, but Jenny Lynn, um,
how far are you from where I'm at?
I I would say I'm right about where you
are. Um when people have asked me how GA
was, I've really focused on uh the
connections I got to make, people I got
to see, uh I haven't talked a lot about
what happened in the assembly room, um
what the what the business looked like,
um because I think think I feel a lot
more ambivalent about that and a lot
more kind of meh about that. Um, but it
was encouraging being able to catch up
with some great brothers and sisters and
have some of that time together um, in
that regard. So, I was grateful for
that.
>> Let's unpack that a little bit more. So,
uh, it was meh. It was adequate. Um, my
typical answer every year from general
assembly is, well, there was some good,
there was some bad. What were what were
one or two things that you thought were
really good? Uh, and what were one two
thing one or two things that you thought
were less than adequate, let's say, as
opposed to bad. Um, what what do you
think? Uh, one thing that was really
good from from my vantage point and you
guys sadly were not a part of this, were
not even invited to this, uh, was we had
a happy hour for women staff, women who
are working in PCA churches, PCA
committees, organizations, and other
adjacent ministries like Serge and came
together and just spent time hanging
out, getting to meet and connect with
one another. And it was incredible to
see. I think we had at least 50 women
gathered. Um, and just to see these
women who are there because they love
the church. Like these are people who
don't necessarily have to be at GA. Most
of them were there by just sheer choice.
Um, not because they were obligated by
their jobs, but to be able to connect
with one another and to see how God was
at work in a variety of places and
people and just different vantage points
on work in the kingdom was really
encouraging. So, that was a highlight
for me.
Yeah, I would say um the fellowship
gathering is an event uh that we put on
every year on Wednesday uh evenings. Uh
so after dinner um we had a fellowship
gathering event. Uh hopefully many of
you watching uh were invited and
attended uh and had an opportunity at
Southside Social to connect um to hear
stories uh to reflect on and to think
about uh just what's happening uh in the
life of the church. And so that was an
incredibly encouraging time for me. Um
there's always this running into folks
some of whom I know well and then
meeting friends, people I'm meeting just
for the first time which is always uh
very very exciting. Um I I would say on
on the business side, one of the
encouraging things uh for me is that
there was a transition. So Will Hus
after many years of faithful leadership
of RUF, which I view is just a key part
to what it means when you think broadly
about the PCA, then if you think about
general assembly, then you don't have to
go that far until you think about um uh
kind of the business side of general
assembly. And so if I shared kind of the
outside the business side, one of the
business highlights for me would be this
successful transition I think after Will
Huss's years of faithful service to see
him be honored uh for all of the work
that he's uh put in and then to see the
search committee from RUF um land on the
recommendation of Andrew Ry is the new
coordinator and to see Andrew navigate
that process is fantastic. Yeah, I agree
with both of y'all in terms of the
social sides of things. My uh our new
director of disciplehip, Leslie
Janikowski, wasn't able to make it to
the Tuesday night fellowship event with
uh female staff because she was teaching
a Bible study and got to Chattanooga
late. Um but I was very encouraged by
all the the women's staff that were
present uh that were there out of Pure
Choice that participated in this event.
Um hugely encouraging. The fellowship
event uh on Wednesday night was amazing.
Um uh I think it was the best one yet
that I've been to. Um it was great to
see so many um hanging out with each
other and especially when Irwin uh
showed up. Uh there was just a general
surrounding uh of our friend u in that
time. Um, I know for me personally the
other fellowship highlight event uh was
every it's kind of our tradition uh at
the churches I've served uh for all the
elders and staff, pastors, all all the
folks uh and their spouses if they came.
Uh we have dinner on Thursday night um
before the worship service. Uh and so we
had
>> uh 15 70 folk 17 folks around the table
um at a local restaurant. It was just uh
I walked into that meeting uh that
dinner kind of discouraged. I I you
know, truth be told and pretty
exhausted. Uh and at the end of the two
and a half hour time together, meal
together, um I I was reminded of why I
do this. uh which is there are faithful
friends um
>> faithful partners in the gospel, women
and men that I serve with uh and um and
the PCA is a good thing to to fight for
um in that regard. Uh and my local folks
reminded me of that which kind of takes
me to some of the the not so good,
right? Um we were talking before we we
pressed record. Um, for me, one of the
not so good, in fact, um, actually
pretty bad parts of General Assembly,
um, was all the things that surrounded,
uh, our mission to North America
coordinator, Irwin, teaching Irwin. Um,
on, uh, on Wednesday, um, the committee
of commissioners uh, was nearly evenly
divided uh, over recommending to the
assembly that Irwin be reelected. Um,
and there was a lengthy floor debate uh
on that uh which to me was incredibly uh
hurtful uh and um I think actually
damaging uh to our bond of trust with
each other. Um not to mention that it
raises any tons of questions on why
anyone would want to be a coordinator or
to to have any role of leadership at the
BCA if this is how we're going to be
treated. But then we followed it up the
next day. Um when the M&A budget uh was
being brought to the floor through the
administrative committee uh and there
was debate over Irwin's salary, there
was actually a motion to cut his salary
10%. Uh and the elder who proposed it um
freely admitted that this was punitive.
Um it it strikes me that there is not a
single elder, ruling elder or teaching
elder, if they were in Irwin's position
that where they would have wanted that
to happen to themselves. Um, I I can't
imagine how awful it would be for me at
my annual meeting uh in August um to to
have to be reelected again. Um to to
have uh to have people question my
leadership in front of me, to have a
motion brought from the floor to cut my
salary as to in a punitive fashion. Uh I
can't imagine how horrific that is. That
would be if I was in issues and yet we
did that to our brother. Um, this is not
the way we ought to be.
Um, part of AMR's kind one of our key
values is is is ultimately the way we
deal with one another has to be for the
flourishing of the church. Uh, as one of
my mentors, Bob Burns, uh, was fond of
saying, how we do things is just as
important as what we do. um we can reach
lots of people with the gospel, but if
we destroy each other in the meantime,
um it raises questions about how we've
reached other people with the gospel. Um
so for me, um uh whatever good uh
happened at General Assembly, uh was uh
was overwhelmed by um that bad. Uh, and
I I trust that that that folks from
every side of the spectrum of the PCA um
share that that wasn't the way should
that should have gone down. Uh, and we
don't want to do that again. Um, that
was that was not good.
>> What about y'all? What were some not so
good things?
>> Well, I feel like it's impossible to
move too quickly away from that in as
much as that that was something from
this year's GA in Chattanooga that will
stick with me. Um and maybe to the
casual observer or someone who hasn't
seen or or understands a lot of general
assemblies, if we could just take a note
to give some some broader perspective
quickly, um virtually every leader of
our agencies, including our state at
clerk, um who who maybe mo most is one
of the most prominent kind of positions
of leadership within the PCA, but if
you're the MTW coordinator, if you're um
the the president of a seminary, all of
these folks, these leaders are operating
effectively on one year terms, right?
So, every year they they come up for
renewal and the their permanent board
will make a recommendation and then the
committee of commissioners can choose to
ratify that and then it comes to the
floor of the assembly. Now, for all of
these positions um throughout the
history of the PCA, this is almost
viewed as a pro-forma exercise. So,
there's almost this agreement. Yes,
you're on a one-year term, but I don't
know that it's ever happened um in the
history of the PCA that someone has come
up for a one-year term and and then at
some point in the process, they've said
no, apart from that person resigning or
retiring, which usually they give
advanced notice of something that will
hust. So, we saw that go well maybe if I
can use RUF as a positive example of
when you would say, oh, that makes sense
that Will Hus wasn't renewed because it
was clear to everyone. Um so to kind of
choose to debate voting yes or no um
when it comes to uh Reverend Dr. Irwin
as the coordinator of M&A was uh in and
of itself no matter what you think about
his role or that position or the person
or his leadership uh we can just say I
think Sean fairly that this is a big
step in a very different direction just
as a broad cultural thing that when you
choose to stand up and enter into debate
over something that uh maybe the average
person's understanding would be wait the
board has said we want Dr. to continue
and and then even the committee of
commissioners while it's debate it uh
still ratified that decision and then
for it to make it to the floor and say
okay let's debate it here that was just
a bit of a departure um from precedent
from culture from norms now I'm not
saying that made it wrong it just was
startling that's part of what made made
it jarring to me being around the PCA
for for a number of years and and
participating in general assembly so
maybe that's helpful if someone says I
don't get it that that it was up for a
vote you vote it. Isn't that how it
usually goes? The short answer is no.
That's not how it usually goes. And if I
hear you right, Sean, you're saying, I
hope it doesn't go that way again.
>> Part of the reason why that Bob Burns is
saying is so important to me. How we do
things is just as important as what we
do is because it's how we do things uh
that's where the gospel gets lived out.
you know, treating one another as not
just image of God, but treating one
another as uh sisters and brothers in
Christ, treating one another as beloved
children of our common heavenly father,
so that we would never want to bring
shame upon another or or bring harm upon
another. Um you know, our our our our
next generations, they they are
watching. Um, and you know, if we if as
the Apostle Paul says in Galatians 5, if
we chew and bite one another, right, we
we ultimately are harming Christ's
little ones. So, you know, as you kind
of link look forward to, you know,
Chattanooga beyond um uh you know, it's
at some levels a perfectly adequate GA
with that massive exception of how we
dealt with um Dr. Ins. Um,
what are you hoping for uh over the next
months as we look towards Louisville uh
and uh next year? Thoughts on that?
Concluding words?
A prayer for all of the state clerks uh
who now have like 13 various items that
they have to get out to their
presetaries to vote on. like there's
like a massive uh amount of BCO changes
among other things that now will go to
presbyaries to take up as business. Um
that's an important part of the
productive side. There are two study
committees that we can be praying for um
who are going to do work on Christian
nationalism as well as the directory of
worship. Um and and so I think that you
know in some ways you can be really
encouraged by um the the church as we
move into the next year. I I was
encouraged on the whole. Um I I think by
the work and business that was done. Um
I I think there's this open question of
how we can choose to try to treat one
another in every venue. Um in every
venue. So whether that's in one-on-one
conversations and hallways, whether
that's in debate from the floor, um
whether that is uh online uh on podcasts
on social media, um I think the church,
the PCA as a whole has a real option
here. Uh we can become more like the
culture and how they are taking up the
news to express, to vent, um to think
out loud. um or we can stand and embody
uh the Christian ethic of loving one
another as we want to be loved um or
following in Jesus's pattern of of love
which doesn't mean and I want to be
clear about this it doesn't mean that
there's no debate it doesn't mean that
um we don't try to pursue truth um for
sure those things are should be exactly
what we're after but how we do that
matters and so my hope as we look to the
next year um that as we have a choice
collectively as a church to do that that
we will choose to be a distinctive
witness in a time where um you will see
frustrations boil over in ways that we
wouldn't think uh embody the Christian
ethic of how we love one another. I
would love to see us um starting with
AMR exec board with uh those who follow
AMR and with others um to try to embody
that as we continue forward.
>> Jenny Lynn, you get the last word. Oh
man, I I think one thing that was
encouraging to me at GA and I think this
came especially at the panel that we
were all part of was I think there are
people who want to listen and want to
slowly and carefully and humbly really
figure out how to move forward well and
how to sit in disagreement well um and
how to learn and and listen to people
with differing views. I think we saw
that in the response to our video
discussion on the overtures with Joel
and and three men who came at things
from different angles, but really were
able to talk together with one another.
Enjoy it. It seemed like you guys were
enjoying that time with one another
even. Um, and there were moments of of
laughter on the assembly floor even
amidst these debates. And I think the
more that we can seek to do that, the
more that we can seek to listen, to be
curious, to have hearts of humility and
be quick to repent, the more that we can
can cultivate that, I think the more
that we have the opportunity to really
grow and reflect the gospel and continue
to see the flourishing of the church as
we go forward and then the flourishing
of the communities around us as well.
Well, that's a great way to conclude
because that's exactly what AMR is
working for. Um, we're working for the
flourishing of God's people um rooted in
the gospel of grace. And so, friends,
thank you for joining us on this panel.
Thank you for watching. Um, hope you
will join us for future uh video
segments that we're producing. Um,
please do check out our website um where
there's lots of resources uh that you
can find there. Um, thank you. We're
we're glad that you were with us.